<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Building HtmlUnit from CVS</title>
        <author email="mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</author>
        <author email="BarnabyCourt@users.sourceforge.net">BarnabyCourt</author>
        <revision>$Revision$</revision>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section>
            <p>
                Building HtmlUnit from the cvs repository will give you the latest version of the code.  At
                any time, all the code in cvs should be compilable and should pass all the unit tests.  There
                is no guarantee that it will be full featured - this is a work in progress.
            </p>
        </section>


        <section name="Checking out">
            <p>
            Create a directory for HtmlUnit (ie c:\htmlunit or ~/htmlunit).  Change to that directory and execute the
            following commands.  When prompted for a password, just press the enter key.
            </p>
            <source>
cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.htmlunit.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/htmlunit login
cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.htmlunit.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/htmlunit co htmlunit
            </source>
            <warning>
                The old directory structure used the modules "src", "docs" and "lib".  These modules are still
                present in cvs but are no longer used.  All current source will be found in the "htmlunit"
                module.
            </warning>
        </section>


        <section name="Compiling the code">
            <p>
                Make sure that you have <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Ant</a> 1.5 installed.
                The build.xml file is located in the root of the src directory so change to that
                directory and execute the following commands
            </p>
            <source>ant initialize</source>
            <p>
                This will get the libraries needed to build that are not in the CVS repository.
            </p>
            <source>ant cleancompile</source>
            <p>
                This will delete all the existing class files and recompile all the source from scratch.
            </p>
        </section>


        <section name="Running the tests">
            <p>
                All the tests are based on <a href="http://www.junit.org/">JUnit</a>.  JUnit is already provided
                in the lib directory so you don't need to install anything extra.  The main tests can be
                executed with either the text runner or the swing runner from JUnit.  The "junit" target
                will dump status information to the command line while "junitui" will present a swing
                user interface with a progress bar.
            </p>
            <source>ant junit</source>
            <br />
            <source>ant junitui</source>
            <p>
                Strangely, the Swing version takes about three times as long to execute as the text runner
                so I rarely use it.  If you are using the Swing version then you will have to uncheck
                "reload classes" or else all the javascript related tests will fail.  It seems that
                the javascript engine and the logging framework don't like to be reloaded.
            </p>
        </section>


        <section name="Packaging the code">
            <source>ant build</source>
            <p>
                The build target will create a directory at the same level as src, lib and docs with the
                name "HtmlUnit-" followed by the version number.  There will also be a zip file of the
                same name that contains the contents of the directory.  Finally, there will be a zip
                called projectdocs.zip that contains all the generated documentation.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
