<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns:j="jelly:core">

    <properties>
        <title>Welcome to HtmlUnit</title>
        <author email="mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</author>
        <revision>$Revision$</revision>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section>
            <p>
                HtmlUnit is a java unit testing framework for testing web based applications.  It is similar
                in concept to
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/httpunit">httpunit</a>
                but is very different in implementation.  Which one is better for you depends on how
                you like to write your tests.  HttpUnit models the http protocol so you deal with request and
                response objects. HtmlUnit on the other hand, models the returned document so that you deal
                with pages and forms and tables.
            </p>
            <p>
                HtmlUnit was originally written by
                <a href="mailto:mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</a> of
                <a href="http://www.GargoyleSoftware.com">Gargoyle Software</a>
                and released under an <a href="license.html">apache style license</a>.  
                Since then, it has received many contributions from <a href="team-list.html">
                other developers</a> and would not be where it is today without their
                assistance.
            </p>
            <p>
                HtmlUnit is not a generic unit testing framework.  It is specifically a way to simulate
                a browser for testing purposes and is intended to be used within another testing
                framework such as <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit</a>.  Refer to the document
                <a href="gettingStarted.html">"Getting Started with HtmlUnit"</a> for an introduction.
            </p>
            <p>
                NOTE: This documentation is for the current code in SVN and may not accurately
                reflect the version of HtmlUnit that you have downloaded.  Refer to the
                documentation that came with your download for the most correct information
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Where to find...">
            <p>
                <dl>
                <!-- The nightly builds are broken at the moment
                    <dt>Nightly Build (highly unstable) <date>Yesterday</date></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <a href="nightly/">
                            Download Nightly Build
                        </a>.
                    </dd>
                -->
                    <dt>Latest stable release <date>Mar 15, 2007</date></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=47038">
                            version 1.11
                        </a>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </p>
            <p>
                Documentation
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadoc API documentation</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="changes-report.html">Change history</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="faq.html">Frequently Asked Questions</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/htmlunit">HtmlUnit project page on SourceForge.net</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=47038">HtmlUnit mailing list</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/phpwiki/index.php">HtmlUnit wiki</a>
                        with an RSS feed for recent changes
                        <a href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/phpwiki/index.php/RecentChanges?format=rss">
                        	   <img src="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/phpwiki/themes/default/buttons/RSS.png" border="0" alt="RSS logo" />
                        </a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="codingConventions.html">HtmlUnit coding conventions</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="submittingBugs.html">Submitting bugs</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="submittingPatches.html">Submitting patches</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="buildingFromSVN.html">Getting and building the most recent code from SVN</a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <p>
                Tutorials
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="gettingStarted.html">Getting Started</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="table-howto.html">Tables</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="logging.html">Logging</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="window-howto.html">Windows and frames</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="keyboard-howto.html">Keyboard navigation</a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Features">
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Support for the HTTP and HTTPS protocols. (
                    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse">JSSE</a>
                    must be in your classpath in order to use HTTPS support)</li>
                    <li>Support for cookies</li>
                    <li>Ability to specify whether failing responses from the server should throw
                    exceptions or should be returned as pages of the appropriate type (based on content
                    type)</li>
                    <li>Support for submit methods POST and GET</li>
                    <li>Ability to customize the request headers being sent to the server</li>
                    <li>Support for html responses
                        <ul>
                            <li>Wrapper for html pages that provides easy access to all information
                            contained inside them</li>
                            <li>Support for submitting forms</li>
                            <li>Support for clicking links</li>
                            <li>Support for walking the DOM model of the html document</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Proxy server support</li>
                    <li>Support for basic authentication</li>
                    <li>Partial support for javascript (see javascript section below)</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Installation">
            <p>
                Place <a href="dependencies.html">all the required jars</a> in your classpath.
                All of these can be found in the lib directory of the HtmlUnit installation.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="JavaScript support">
            <p>
                Starting with the 1.1 release, HtmlUnit is supporting javascript.  The core
                javascript language is already fully supported by the Rhino javascript engine.  The
                web browser specific host objects are being implemented now.  We are focussing on
                those parts of javascript that are most commonly used first and will flesh out the
                remaining javascript support over time.  If there is something specific that you
                need that we haven't got to yet then please open a feature request.  We are
                prioritizing tasks according to demand so if you want a specific feature then
                make sure we know about it (opening a feature request is still the best way to
                do that).
            </p>
            <note title="Disabling JavaScript support">
                <p>
                    To disable JavaScript processing for one WebClient, call WebClient.setJavaScriptEnabled(false).
                </p>
            </note>
            <p>
                Javascript code in script tags will get executed when the page loads. If
                you want to execute code after that, you can call
                HtmlPage.executeJavascriptIfPossible(String).
            </p>
            <p>
                Refer to the changes document for details on what is being added.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

