<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Submitting Bugs</title>
        <author>Chris Erskine</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section>
            <p>
                For JavaScript Bugs, please read <a href="submittingJSBugs.html">this</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Bugs are a constant problem with software development.  In HtmlUnit, there are several factors
                for the cause of bugs.  These include: bugs in third-party code, functionality that still is not
                supported by HtmlUnit, bugs in your code, or true bugs in HtmlUnit.  To track these bugs, we are
                using the SourceForge issue tracking system located at 
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=47038&amp;atid=448266">
                http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=47038&amp;atid=448266</a>
            </p>
            <p>
                Before reporting an error, make sure that you are up to the latest version of the software.  If
                you can, get the <a href="https://ci.canoo.com/teamcity/viewLog.html?buildTypeId=HtmlUnit_FastBuild&amp;buildId=lastSuccessful&amp;tab=artifacts">latest snapshot</a>,
                or build it from Subversion to see if the error still occurs.  Check the 
                <a href="dependencies.html">dependencies</a> to be sure that you have all the required jar files.
                Also, review the list of bugs and recently closed bugs to see if someone else has already reported
                the bug.  If they have, you may want to just add more detail to it. 
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="How to submit reports that get responses">
            <p>
                Development of HtmlUnit is done as a volunteer effort.  As such, the developers respond when they
                get a chance.  There are a number of things that you can do to help get a quicker response
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Describe the bug in as much detail as possible.  To be able to fix a bug, the developer
                        has to be able to reproduce it. The more detail provided, the easier this is to do. Include
                        the source code that you have to produce the bug and the HTML page.  Reduce this down to the
                        least amount of code required to produce the error on both the executing code and the HTML.
                        If the developer has to look through 2 pages 
                        of HTML and JavaScript to see what is happening, it may not happen.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        If you can, write a <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit</a> test that reproduces the error.
                        This makes it much easier to find the bug since the developer has to just run the unit test to
                        reproduce the error.
                   </li>
                   <li>
                        Best is to review the code and find what is causing the bug and not only write a unit test that
                        produces the bug, but also a patch that fixes the bug.  Include these files in the bug report
                        following the rules for <a href="submittingPatches.html">submitting patches.</a>
                   </li>
               </ul>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

