<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document title="Welcome to HtmlUnit">

<section title="HtmlUnit Overview">
	<p>
		HtmlUnit is a java unit testing framework for testing web based applications.  It is similar
		in concept to
		<a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/httpunit">httpunit</a>
		but is very different in implementation.  Which one is better for you depends on how
		you like to write your tests.  HttpUnit models the http protocol so you deal with request and
		response objects. HtmlUnit on the other hand, models the returned document so that you deal
		with pages and form and tables.
	</p>
	<p>
		HtmlUnit was written by
		<a href="mailto:mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</a> of
		<a href="http://www.GargoyleSoftware.com">Gargoyle Software</a>
		and has been released under an <a href="license.html">apache style license</a>
	</p>
</section>

<section title="Where to find...">
	<p>
		<dl>
			<dt>Latest stable release <date>November 25, 2002</date></dt>
			<dd>Version <b>1.1 final</b>: |
				<a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/htmlunit/HtmlUnit-1.1.zip?download">Download</a> |
				<a href="api/index.html">Javadoc API documentation</a> |
				<a href="changes.html">Change history</a> |
			</dd>
		</dl>
	</p>
<!--
	<p>
		<dl>
			<dt>Current development release</dt>
			<dd>Version <b>1.1rc1</b>: |
				<a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/htmlunit/HtmlUnit-1.1-rc1.zip?download">Download</a> |
				<a href="api/index.html">Javadoc API documentation</a> |
				<a href="changes.html">Change history</a> |
				<br />
				<warning title="Important Note">
					The goal of 1.1 was to provide a level of javascript support that would handle
					the most common cases.  I believe that goal has now been met.  Assuming there are
					no show-stopper bugs found, this build will become 1.1 final.
				</warning>
			</dd>
		</dl>
	</p>
-->
	<p>
		<dl>
			<dt>Most recent code</dt>
			<dd>
				<a href="buildingFromCvs.html">Getting and building the most recent code from CVS</a>
			</dd>
		</dl>
	</p>
	<p>
		<dl>
			<dt>Other information</dt>
			<dd>
				<a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/htmlunit">HtmlUnit project page on SourceForge.net</a>
				<br />
				<a href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=47038">HtmlUnit mailing list</a>
				<br />
				<a href="codingConventions.html">HtmlUnit coding conventions</a>
				<br />
				<a href="submittingPatches.html">Submitting patches</a>
			</dd>
		</dl>
	</p>

	<p>
		<dl>
			<dt>Tutorials</dt>
			<dd> |
				<a href="table-howto.html">Tables</a> |
				<a href="logging.html">Logging</a> |
				<a href="window-howto.html">Windows and frames</a> |
				<a href="keyboard-howto.html">Keyboard navigation</a> |
				<br />
			</dd>
		</dl>
	</p>
</section>


<section title="Features">
	<p>
		<ul>
			<li>Support for the HTTP and HTTPS protocols. (
			<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse">JSSE</a>
			must be in your classpath in order to use HTTPS support)</li>
			<li>Support for cookies</li>
			<li>Ability to specify whether failing responses from the server should throw
			exceptions or should be returned as pages of the appropriate type (based on content
			type)</li>
			<li>Support for submit methods POST and GET</li>
			<li>Ability to customize the request headers being sent to the server</li>
			<li>Support for html responses
				<ul>
					<li>Wrapper for html pages that provides easy access to all information
					contained inside them</li>
					<li>Support for submitting forms</li>
					<li>Support for clicking links</li>
					<li>Support for walking the DOM model of the html document</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>Proxy server support</li>
			<li>Support for basic authentication</li>
			<li>Partial support for javascript (see javascript section below)</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
</section>

<section title="Installation">
	<p>
		Place the following jar files in your classpath.  All of these can be found in the lib directory
		of the HtmlUnit installation.
	</p>
	<p>
		<dl>
			<dt>HtmlUnit.jar</dt>
			<dd>The main HtmlUnit classes</dd>

			<dt>commons-httpclient.jar <version-string>Dec 9/2002 build</version-string></dt>
			<dd><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/httpclient/">HttpClient from Apache</a>,
			the code that actually handles the http connections.  Note that commons-httpclient
			is going through active development and does not have a stable release yet.  We're
			using periodic "daily snapshots" which are actually quite solid.</dd>

			<dt>commons-logging.jar <version-string>1.0.2</version-string></dt>
			<dd><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/logging.html">Logging
			from Apache</a></dd>

			<dt>nekohtml.jar <version-string>0.7.1</version-string></dt>
			<dd><a href="http://www.apache.org/~andyc/neko/doc/html/index.html">
			NekoHTML</a> is a tool to convert badly written html into an xml
			dom model</dd>

			<dt>xercesImpl.jar and xmlParserAPIs.jar <version-string>2.1.0</version-string></dt>
			<dd>The<a href="http://xml.apache.org/xerces2-j/index.html">
			Xerces</a> xml parser from Apache. </dd>

			<dt>js.jar <version-string>1.5R3</version-string></dt>
			<dd><a href="http://www.mozilla.org/rhino">Rhino</a>,
			a javascript engine from the Mozilla project.  This jar is optional - if it isn't
			found then javascript support will be disabled but the rest of HtmlUnit will
			continue to work.</dd>

		</dl>
		<note>
			If you want to use HTTPS (Secure HTTP) then you will have to have the JSSE in your
			classpath.  JSSE is a standard part of Java starting with JDK1.4.  If you are using
			an earlier version of Java, then you can
			<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse">download</a> the JSSE from the Sun website.
		</note>
	</p>
</section>

<section title="JavaScript support">
	<p>
		Starting with the 1.1 release, HtmlUnit is supporting javascript.  The core
		javascript language is already fully supported by the Rhino javascript engine.  The
		web browser specific host objects are being implemented now.  We are focussing on
		those parts of javascript that are most commonly used first and will flesh out the
		remaining javascript support over time.  If there is something specific that you
		need that we haven't got to yet then please open a feature request.  We are
		prioritizing tasks according to demand so if you want a specific feature then
		make sure we know about it (opening a feature request is still the best way to
		do that).
	</p>
	<note title="Disabling JavaScript support">
		<p>
			To disable JavaScript processing for one WebClient, call WebClient.setJavaScriptEnabled(false).
		</p>
		<p>
			To disable JavaScript processing for all WebClients, remove js.jar from your classpath
		</p>
	</note>
	<p>
		Javascript code in script tags will get executed when the page loads.  If
		you want to execute code after that, you can call
		HtmlPage.executeJavascriptIfPossible(String).
	</p>
	<p>
		Refer to the changes document for details on what is being added.
	</p>
</section>


</document>

