<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document title="Submitting patches">

<section>
	<p>
		Contributions are always welcome but please note the following:
		<ul>
			<li>
				Make sure the code follows the <a href="codingConventions.html">coding conventions</a>
				already in use.  Failing to do this just means more work for the maintainers as the
				code will have to be "cleaned up" prior to merging.  Refer to the link above to
				see the coding conventions that we are using here.  We use checkstyle to enforce
				many of the coding standards (some things like good naming can't be easily checked
				with a tool but we check as much as we can automatically).  The ant target
				"checkstyle" will check all the code.
			</li>
			<li>
				Make sure the new code has automated unit tests written for
				<a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit</a>.  No code will get merged without tests so
				if you don't do this then once again, it makes work for the maintainers.
			</li>
			<li>
				All unit tests should pass.  Occassionally this rule will be broken if it is important
				to get a test into the build before the code is ready.
			</li>
			<li>
				All files must be copyright Gargoyle Software and must be licensed under the same
				license as the rest of the probject - currently an <a href="license.html">apache
				style</a> one.
			</li>
			<li>
				All non-private methods must have full javadoc before we put out a release.  If you
				make changes to a given file then you are expected to add an author tag at the top
				of the file.  @author tags are written in chronological order with the original
				author at the top.  Refer to <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/javadoc/writingdoccomments/">
				How to Write JavaDoc</a> for more specific information on javadoc.
			</li>
		</ul>
		Patches are more likely to be accepted if there isn't a lot of extra work for the
		maintainers to do before committing.
	</p>
	<p>
		Additional documentation or code samples are always appreciated.  We're focussed on writing
		code and documentation often gets neglected.
	</p>
</section>


</document>

