<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>Details about HtmlUnit</title>
        <author>RBRi</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Request headers">
            <p>
                HtmlUnit mimics the browser as close as possible, of course this includes the sent request headers also.
                But you can change this if needed at two levels; the request level and the client level.<br/>
                To change the request header at the client level use WebClient.addRequestHeader(). You are able to
                add additional headers to every request made by this client or overwrite the default ones.<br/>
                Example: add an addition header to every client request
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[client.addRequestHeader("from htmlunit", "yes");]]></source>
            <p>
                To change the request header at the client level use WebClient.addRequestHeader().<br/>
                Example: replace the default accept-language header for all request made by this client.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[client.addRequestHeader(HttpHeader.ACCEPT_LANGUAGE, "fr");]]></source>
            <p>
                Example: replace the default accept-language header for all request made by this client.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[client.addRequestHeader(HttpHeader.ACCEPT_LANGUAGE, fromClient);]]></source>
            <p>
                Example: replace the default accept-language header for all request made by this client.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[client.addRequestHeader(HttpHeader.ACCEPT_LANGUAGE, fromClient);]]></source>
            <p>
                It is also possible to add/overwrite a request header for a dedicated request.
                Example:
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
WebRequest wr = new WebRequest(URL_FIRST);
wr.setAdditionalHeader("from htmlunit", "yes");
....
client .getPage(wr);
]]></source>
        </section>

        <section name="Attachments">
            <p>
                A handler for attachments, which represent pages received from the server which contain
                Content-Disposition=attachment headers. Normally pages are loaded inline: clicking on
                a link, for example, loads the linked page in the current window. Attached pages are different
                in that they are intended to be loaded outside of this flow: clicking on a link prompts the
                user to either save the linked page, or open it outside of the current window, but does not
                load the page in the current window.
            </p>
            <p>
                HtmlUnit complies with the semantics described above when an <tt>AttachmentHandler</tt> has
                been registered with the com.gargoylesoftware.htmlunit.WebClient via
                com.gargoylesoftware.htmlunit.WebClient#setAttachmentHandler(AttachmentHandler). When
                no attachment handler has been registered with the <tt>WebClient</tt>, the semantics described
                above to not apply, and attachments are loaded inline. By default, <tt>AttachmentHandler</tt>s
                are not registered with new <tt>WebClient</tt> instances.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
