<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>JavaScript Support</title>
        <author email="mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</author>
        <revision>$Revision$</revision>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section>
            <p>
                Core language support for JavaScript is provided by the
                <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/rhino">Mozilla Rhino</a> engine.  What HtmlUnit provides
                are all the browser specific host objects such as Document or Navigator.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="SimpleScriptable">
            <p>
                All of HtmlUnit's JavaScript objects subclass SimpleScripable either directly or indirectly.
                This class contains all the common methods needed by the HtmlUnit host objects.  Additionally,
                it changes the way that JavaScript method lookup happens.  The rhino engine doesn't walk
                up the class hierarchy when looking for methods starting with jsGet_, jsSet_ or jsFunction.
                SimpleScriptable changes this so that the superclass hierarchy is walked.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Debugging JavaScript Errors">
            <p>
                Testing pages with JavaScript on them can produce a number of errors.  These errors occur for
                several reasons.  Some browsers accept shortcuts that are not part of the DOM model and currently not
                duplicated by HtmlUnit.  Also, HtmlUnit still does not implement all of the extensions that have been
                added by the different browsers.  HtmlUnit wraps the inline code into a wrapper function but when
                errors are reported from this code, it is hard to determine what code was really being called.  A
                custom logger has been added to HtmlUnit to support this.  If you set 
                'com.gargoylesoftware.htmlunit.javascript' to debug level, the
                inline code will be logged with the wrapper function to help you determine what line of code is failing.
            </p>
            <p>
                One of the problems with JavaScript is finding the objects that you expect to be defined but have not
                been defined within the code.  To help find some of these errors, HtmlUnit will produce WARN level messages
                reporting these errors. Before submitting JavaScript bugs, please read <a href="submittingJSBugs.html">this</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
