<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>JavaScript Tutorial</title>
        <author email="mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</author>
        <revision>$Revision$</revision>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>
                A frequent question we get is "how do I test my JavaScript?".
                There is nothing really specific for using JavaScript, it is automatically processed.
                So, you just need to .getPage(), find the element to click(), and then check the result.
                Tests for complex JavaScript libraries are included in HtmlUnit test base, you can find it
                <a href="http://htmlunit.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/htmlunit/trunk/htmlunit/src/test/java/com/gargoylesoftware/htmlunit/libraries/">here</a>
                which is useful to get an idea.
            </p>
            <p>
                Usually, you should wait() or sleep() a little, as HtmlUnit can finish before the AJAX response is
                retrieved from the server, please read <a href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/faq.html#AJAXDoesNotWork">this FAQ</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Below are some examples:
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Example: using Document.write()">
            <p>
                Lets say that we have a page containing JavaScript that will dynamically
                write content to the page.  The following html will dynamically generate
                five textfields and place them inside a table.  Each textfield will have
                a unique name created by appending the index to the string "textfield".
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
<html><head><title>Table sample</title></head><body>
    <form action='/foo' name='form1'>
    <table id="table1">
        <script type="text/javascript">
            for (i = 1; i <= 5; i++) {
                document.write("<tr><td>" + i
                    + "</td><td><input name='textfield" + i
                    + "' type='text'></td></tr>");
            }
        </script>
    </table></form>
</body></html>]]></source>
            
            <p>
                We would likely want to test that the five text fields were created so
                we could start with this.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
@Test
public void documentWrite() throws Exception {
    final WebClient webClient = new WebClient();

    final HtmlPage page = webClient.getPage("http://myserver/test.html");
    final HtmlForm form = page.getFormByName("form1");
    for (int i = 1; i <= 5; i++) {
        final String expectedName = "textfield" + i;
        Assert.assertEquals(
            "text", 
            form.<HtmlInput>getInputByName(expectedName).getTypeAttribute());
    }
}]]></source>
            <p>
                We might also want to check off-by-one errors by ensuring that 
                it didn't create "textfield0" or "textfield6".  Trying to get an 
                element that doesn't exist will cause an exception to be thrown
                so we could add this to the end of the previous test.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
try {
    form.getInputByName("textfield0");
    fail("Expected an ElementNotFoundException");
}
catch (final ElementNotFoundException e) {
    // Expected path
}

try {
    form.getInputByName("textfield6");
    fail("Expected an ElementNotFoundException");
}
catch (final ElementNotFoundException e) {
    // Expected path
}]]></source>
        </section>
        
        <section name="Example: Watching for 'alerts'">
            <p>
                Often you want to watch alerts triggered by JavaScript.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
<html><head><title>Alert sample</title></head>
<body onload='alert("foo");'>
</body></html>]]></source>
            <p>
               Alerts are tracked by an AlertHandler which will be called whenever
               the JavaScript alert() function is called.  In the following test, 
               we register an alert handler which just saves all messages into a 
               list.  When the page load is complete, we compare that list of
               collected alerts with another list of expected alerts to ensure
               they are the same.
            </p>

            <source><![CDATA[
@Test
public void alerts() throws Exception {
    final WebClient webClient = new WebClient();

    final List collectedAlerts = new ArrayList();
    webClient.setAlertHandler(new CollectingAlertHandler(collectedAlerts));

    // Since we aren't actually manipulating the page, we don't assign
    // it to a variable - it's enough to know that it loaded.
    webClient.getPage("http://tciludev01/test.html");

    final List expectedAlerts = Collections.singletonList("foo");
    Assert.assertEquals(expectedAlerts, collectedAlerts);
}]]></source>
        </section>
        
        <section name="Prompts, Confirms and Status line messages">
            <p>
                Handling prompt dialogs, confirm dialogs and status line messages
                work in the same way as alerts.  You register a handler of the 
                appropriate type and it will get notified when that method is called.
                See WebClient.setPromptHandler(), WebClient.setConfirmHandler() and
                WebClient.setStatusHandler() for details on these.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Event handlers">
            <p>
                Most event handlers are already implemented: onload, onclick, ondblclick, onmouseup, onsubmit, onreadystatechange, ... 
                They will be triggered at the appropriate time just like in a "real browser".  
            </p>
            <p>
            	If the event that you wish to test is not yet supported then you can 
            	directly invoke it through the ScriptEngine.  Note that while the script 
            	engine is publicly 
                accessible, we do not recommend using it directly unless you have no
                other choice.  It is much better to manipulate the page as a user would
                by clicking on elements and shifting the focus around.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>

</document>
