<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Keyboard Navigation Tutorial</title>
        <author email="mbowler@GargoyleSoftware.com">Mike Bowler</author>
        <revision>$Revision$</revision>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section>
            <p>
                For a given WebClient, the focus can be on at most one element at any given time.  Focus
                doesn't have to be on any element within the WebClient.
            </p>
            <p>
                There are several ways to move the focus from one element to another.  The simplest is to call
                HtmlPage.setFocusedElement(HtmlElement).
                This method will remove focus from whatever element currently has it, if any, and will set
                it to the new component.  Along the way, it will fire off any "onfocus" and "onblur" handlers
                that have been defined.
            </p>
            <p>
                The element currently owning the focus can be determined with a call to
                HtmlPage.getFocusedElement().
            </p>
            <p>
                To simulate keyboard navigation via the tab key, you can call
                HtmlPage.tabToNextElement() and HtmlPage.tabToPreviousElement()
                to cycle forward or backwards through the defined tab order.  This tab order is
                defined by the
                <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/interact/forms.html#adef-tabindex">tabindex</a>
                attribute on the various elements as defined by the HTML specification.  You can query
                the defined tab order with the method
                HtmlPage.getTabbableElements()
                which will return a list of all tabbable elements in defined tab order.
            </p>
            <p>
                Access keys, often called keyboard mnemonics, can be simulated with the method
                HtmlPage.pressAccessKey(char).
            </p>
            <p>
                To use special keys, you can use htmlElement.type(int) with KeyboardEvent.DOM_VK_PAGE_DOWN.
            </p>
            <p>
                Finally, there is an assertion for testing that will verify that every tabbable element
                has a defined tabindex attribute.  This is done with
                WebAssert.assertAllTabIndexAttributesSet().
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>

</document>

