<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="https://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 https://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>Details about HtmlUnit Security</title>
        <author>RBRi</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Content" id="content">
            <macro name="toc">
            </macro>
        </section>

        <section name="Overview" id="sec_overview">
            <p>
                HtmlUnit is a headless browser written in Java for testing, automation, and web scraping.
                It provides implementations of browser technologies such as HTML parsing, the DOM,
                JavaScript execution, cookies, networking, and browser APIs.
            </p>
            <p>
                Unlike modern web browsers such as Chrome, Firefox, or Edge,
                <strong>HtmlUnit is not designed to provide a secure execution environment
                for untrusted web content</strong>.
                While it aims to emulate browser behavior, it intentionally does
                <strong>not</strong> implement the operating system and process-level
                security architecture found in modern browsers.
            </p>
            <p>
                <strong>Important:</strong>
                HtmlUnit is intended for browser automation and testing—not as a security sandbox.
                Applications that process arbitrary or hostile web content should provide
                appropriate isolation using operating system, virtual machine, container,
                or service-level controls.
            </p>
            <p>
                If your application loads arbitrary or untrusted web pages, you are responsible
                for providing appropriate isolation and restricting the privileges of the
                HtmlUnit process.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Security Considerations" id="sec_security_considerations">
            <p>
                HtmlUnit executes entirely within the hosting JVM. HTML parsing, DOM processing,
                JavaScript execution, networking, and browser emulation all run as part
                of your application's process.
                <br/>
                This architecture provides excellent integration and performance for
                testing and automation, but it also means that HtmlUnit should
                <strong>not</strong> be considered a security boundary.
            </p>
            <p>
                Unlike modern browsers, HtmlUnit does not provide:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Renderer process isolation</li>
                <li>Operating system sandboxing</li>
                <li>Site isolation</li>
                <li>Privilege separation between browser components</li>
                <li>Browser exploit mitigation technologies</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                Applications requiring these protections should execute HtmlUnit inside
                an appropriately isolated environment.
            </p>

        </section>
        
        <section name="Processing Untrusted Content" id="sec_processing_untrusted_content">
            <p>
                Processing arbitrary Internet pages or user-supplied content means parsing
                complex HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and related web content inside your
                application's JVM. As with any software that processes untrusted input,
                vulnerabilities may exist despite ongoing maintenance and security fixes.
            </p>
            <p>
                Examples include:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>User-provided URLs</li>
                <li>Customer-supplied HTML</li>
                <li>Unknown third-party websites</li>
                <li>Malware or security research</li>
                <li>Phishing sites</li>
                <li>Third-party advertising networks</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                While HtmlUnit strives to correctly implement web standards and promptly
                address reported security issues, it should
                <strong>not</strong> be relied upon as the primary security mechanism
                for hostile content.
            </p>
        </section>
        
        <section name="Deployment Recommendations" id="sec_deployment_recommendations">
            <p>
                When processing untrusted or arbitrary web content, consider running
                HtmlUnit inside an isolated environment such as:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A dedicated virtual machine</li>
                <li>A container with limited privileges</li>
                <li>An ephemeral worker process</li>
                <li>A restricted user account</li>
                <li>A separate service with limited permissions</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                When processing untrusted content, the execution environment should be
                considered disposable and recoverable.
            </p>
        
            <subsection name="Security Responsibility Model">
                <p>
                    HtmlUnit focuses on browser emulation and automation functionality.
                    Security controls such as process isolation, network restrictions,
                    resource limits, credential management, monitoring, and workload
                    isolation remain the responsibility of the hosting application and
                    deployment environment.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Network Security">
                <p>
                    HtmlUnit performs network requests on behalf of loaded pages.
                    <br/>
                    Depending on your application, consider:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Restricting outbound network access</li>
                    <li>Using an allow-list of permitted destinations</li>
                    <li>Routing requests through a proxy</li>
                    <li>Preventing access to internal services</li>
                    <li>Protecting against Server-Side Request Forgery (SSRF)</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    Without appropriate controls, untrusted pages may be able to initiate
                    requests to resources accessible from the hosting environment,
                    including internal services, administrative interfaces, or cloud
                    metadata endpoints.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="File System and System Resources">
                <p>
                    HtmlUnit executes within the hosting JVM and should not be treated as
                    a security boundary.
                    <br/>
                    If an attacker successfully exploits a vulnerability in HtmlUnit,
                    one of its dependencies, the Java runtime, or related components,
                    the resulting impact would generally be limited only by the
                    privileges of the hosting process.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Depending on the application's permissions, this could include access to:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Files accessible to the process</li>
                    <li>Network connectivity</li>
                    <li>Environment variables</li>
                    <li>Configuration files</li>
                    <li>Credentials or authentication tokens available to the process</li>
                    <li>Other operating system resources available to the JVM</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    Run HtmlUnit with the minimum operating system permissions required
                    for your application.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Java Security Manager">
                <p>
                    Older Java versions supported the Java Security Manager as an
                    application sandbox.
                    <br/>
                    Since the Security Manager has been deprecated and removed from
                    recent Java releases, applications should instead rely on operating
                    system, container, or virtual machine isolation when processing
                    untrusted content.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        
            <subsection name="Dependency Updates">
                <p>
                    Like any software that processes untrusted input, HtmlUnit and its
                    dependencies should be kept up to date.
                    <br/>
                    Likewise, keep the Java runtime and operating system updated, since
                    vulnerabilities in either may affect the security of applications
                    using HtmlUnit.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        
            <subsection name="Resource Consumption">
                <p>
                    Malicious or poorly written web pages may consume excessive CPU time,
                    memory, network bandwidth, or other system resources.
                </p>
                <p>
                    When processing untrusted content, consider enforcing:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Execution time limits</li>
                    <li>Memory limits</li>
                    <li>CPU quotas</li>
                    <li>Maximum page or response sizes</li>
                    <li>Network request limits</li>
                    <li>Automatic termination and recovery of stalled or misbehaving workloads</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
