<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="https://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 https://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>Details about HtmlUnit Security</title>
        <author>RBRi</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Content" id="content">
            <macro name="toc">
            </macro>
        </section>

        <section name="Overview" id="sec_overview">
            <p>
                HtmlUnit is a headless browser written in Java for testing, automation, and web scraping.
                It provides implementations of browser technologies such as HTML parsing, the DOM, JavaScript execution, 
                cookies, networking, and browser APIs.
            </p>

            <p>
                Unlike modern web browsers such as Chrome, Firefox, or Edge, <strong>HtmlUnit is not designed to
                provide a secure execution environment for untrusted web content</strong>.
                While it aims to emulate browser behavior, it intentionally does <strong>not</strong> implement
                the operating system and process-level security architecture found in modern browsers.
            </p>

            <p>
                If your application loads arbitrary or untrusted web pages, you are responsible for providing appropriate isolation 
                and restricting the privileges of the HtmlUnit process.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Security Considerations"  id="sec_security_considerations">
            <p>
                HtmlUnit executes entirely within the hosting JVM. JavaScript, DOM processing, 
                networking, and browser emulation all run as part of your application's process.<br></br>
                This architecture provides excellent integration and performance for testing and automation, 
                but it also means that HtmlUnit should <strong>not</strong> be considered a security boundary.
            </p>
            <p>
                Unlike modern browsers, HtmlUnit does not provide:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Renderer process isolation</li>
                <li>Operating system sandboxing</li>
                <li>Site isolation</li>
                <li>Privilege separation between browser components</li>
                <li>Browser exploit mitigation technologies</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                Applications that require these protections should execute HtmlUnit inside an appropriately isolated environment.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Processing Untrusted Content"  id="sec_processing_untrusted_content">
            <p>
                Processing arbitrary Internet pages or user-supplied content means executing complex parsing and
                JavaScript code within your application's JVM. As with any software that processes untrusted input,
                vulnerabilities may exist despite ongoing maintenance and security fixes.
            </p>
            <p>
                Examples include:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>User-provided URLs</li>
                <li>Customer-supplied HTML</li>
                <li>Unknown third-party websites</li>
                <li>Malware analysis</li>
                <li>Phishing sites</li>
                <li>Advertisement networks</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                While HtmlUnit makes every effort to correctly implement web standards and fix security defects, 
                it should <strong>not</strong> be relied upon as the primary security mechanism for hostile content.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Deployment Recommendations"  id="sec_deployment_recommendations">
            <p>
                When processing untrusted or arbitrary web content, consider running HtmlUnit inside an isolated environment such as:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A dedicated virtual machine</li>
                <li>A container with limited privileges</li>
                <li>An ephemeral worker process</li>
                <li>A restricted user account</li>
                <li>A separate service with limited permissions</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                If HtmlUnit processes untrusted content, the execution environment should be considered disposable and recoverable.
            </p>

            <subsection name="Network Security">
                <p>
                    HtmlUnit performs network requests on behalf of the loaded page.<br></br>
                    Depending on your application, consider:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Restricting outbound network access</li>
                    <li>Using an allow-list of permitted destinations</li>
                    <li>Routing requests through a proxy</li>
                    <li>Preventing access to internal services</li>
                    <li>Protecting against Server-Side Request Forgery (SSRF)</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="File System and System Resources">
                <p>
                    HtmlUnit does not provide any sandbox or security boundary between the processed web page and the hosting JVM/System.
                    <br></br>
                    Any vulnerability in HtmlUnit or one of its dependencies executes with the full privileges of the hosting process.
                    This includes access to the file system, network, environment variables, credentials available to the process, 
                    and any other resources accessible to the JVM.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Run HtmlUnit with the minimum operating system permissions required for your application.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Java Security Manager">
                <p>
                    Older Java versions supported the Java Security Manager as an application sandbox.
                    <br></br>
                    Since the Security Manager has been deprecated and removed from recent Java releases,
                    applications should use operating system or container-based isolation when processing untrusted content.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Dependency Updates">
                <p>
                    Like any software that processes untrusted input, HtmlUnit and its dependencies should be kept up to date.
                    <br></br>
                    Likewise, keep the Java runtime and operating system up to date, since vulnerabilities in either may affect 
                    the security of applications using HtmlUnit.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Resource Consumption">
                <p>
                    Malicious or poorly written web pages may consume excessive CPU time, memory, or network resources.
                    When processing untrusted content, applications should consider enforcing appropriate resource limits,
                    execution timeouts, and memory limits through the hosting environment.
                </p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
